<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<certification-exam xmlns="http://certification.study/schema/v1" version="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <exam-code>AZ-900</exam-code>
    <exam-title>Microsoft Azure Fundamentals</exam-title>
    <provider>Microsoft</provider>
    <description>Scenario-Based Study Companion for AZ-900 certification - validates foundational knowledge of cloud concepts, Azure services, security, privacy, compliance, and pricing.</description>
    <total-questions>50</total-questions>
    <created-date>2026-01-20</created-date>
    <last-modified>2026-01-20T00:00:00Z</last-modified>
    <categories>
      <category id="cat-cloud-concepts">Cloud Concepts</category>
      <category id="cat-core-services">Core Azure Services</category>
      <category id="cat-security">Security and Compliance</category>
      <category id="cat-pricing">Pricing and Support</category>
      <category id="cat-governance">Governance and Management</category>
    </categories>
  </metadata>

  <questions>
    <question id="1" category-ref="cat-cloud-concepts" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Cloud Computing Benefits</title>
      <scenario>A startup needs to launch a web application quickly without purchasing servers. They want to pay only for what they use and scale during traffic spikes.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which cloud computing benefit best describes paying only for resources consumed?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Consumption-based model (OpEx)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Capital expenditure (CapEx)</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Dedicated hardware allocation</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Fixed monthly pricing</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Cloud computing uses a pay-as-you-go model, which is operational expenditure.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>The consumption-based model (OpEx) means you pay for cloud resources as you use them, rather than investing upfront in hardware (CapEx). This allows startups to avoid large initial investments.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>OpEx (operational expenditure) allows deducting costs in the same year they occur.</li>
              <li>CapEx requires upfront investment and depreciation over time.</li>
              <li>Cloud's consumption model improves cash flow and reduces financial risk for new projects.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Cloud Economics</tag>
        <tag>OpEx vs CapEx</tag>
        <tag>Cost Management</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="2" category-ref="cat-cloud-concepts" difficulty="basic">
      <title>High Availability Concept</title>
      <scenario>An e-commerce company requires their website to remain accessible even if a datacenter fails.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which cloud characteristic ensures a system remains operational despite component failures?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">High availability</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Elasticity</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Agility</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Geo-distribution</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>High availability focuses on keeping systems running with minimal downtime.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>High availability means designing systems to remain operational even when components fail. Azure provides availability zones and regions to achieve this through redundancy.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Azure SLAs define uptime guarantees (e.g., 99.99% for availability zones).</li>
              <li>High availability is measured by uptime percentage and recovery time.</li>
              <li>Elasticity is about scaling; agility is about rapid deployment; geo-distribution is about global presence.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>High Availability</tag>
        <tag>Reliability</tag>
        <tag>Cloud Benefits</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="3" category-ref="cat-cloud-concepts" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Scalability Types</title>
      <scenario>A video streaming service needs to handle millions of concurrent viewers during a live event, then reduce capacity afterward.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which type of scaling adds more VM instances to handle increased load?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Horizontal scaling (scale out)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Vertical scaling (scale up)</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Manual scaling only</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Fixed capacity allocation</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Adding more instances is horizontal scaling; adding more power to existing instances is vertical scaling.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Horizontal scaling (scale out/in) adds or removes VM instances. Vertical scaling (scale up/down) increases or decreases the size/power of existing VMs. Horizontal scaling is typically preferred for web workloads.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Horizontal scaling has no theoretical limit; vertical scaling is limited by maximum VM sizes.</li>
              <li>Azure Virtual Machine Scale Sets automate horizontal scaling.</li>
              <li>Stateless applications scale horizontally more easily than stateful ones.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Scalability</tag>
        <tag>Elasticity</tag>
        <tag>Virtual Machines</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="4" category-ref="cat-cloud-concepts" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Cloud Service Models</title>
      <scenario>A company wants to deploy custom applications without managing operating systems, patching, or runtime environments.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which cloud service model provides a platform for deploying applications without managing underlying infrastructure?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Platform as a Service (PaaS)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS)</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Software as a Service (SaaS)</choice>
        <choice letter="D">On-premises deployment</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>PaaS handles the platform; you focus on your application code.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>PaaS (Platform as a Service) provides a managed platform including OS, middleware, and runtime. You deploy your code; Azure manages everything below. Azure App Service is a common PaaS example.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>IaaS: You manage OS and above; Azure manages hardware/virtualization.</li>
              <li>PaaS: You manage application and data; Azure manages OS, runtime, middleware.</li>
              <li>SaaS: You use the software; provider manages everything (e.g., Microsoft 365).</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Service Models</tag>
        <tag>PaaS</tag>
        <tag>IaaS</tag>
        <tag>SaaS</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="5" category-ref="cat-cloud-concepts" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Public vs Private Cloud</title>
      <scenario>A hospital must keep patient records on infrastructure they fully control due to regulatory requirements, but wants cloud benefits for non-sensitive workloads.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which cloud deployment model combines on-premises infrastructure with public cloud services?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Hybrid cloud</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Public cloud only</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Private cloud only</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Community cloud</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Hybrid cloud combines private/on-premises resources with public cloud.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Hybrid cloud allows organizations to keep sensitive data on-premises (private cloud) while leveraging public cloud for scalable, less-sensitive workloads. Azure Arc helps manage hybrid environments.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Hybrid requires connectivity between environments (VPN, ExpressRoute).</li>
              <li>Azure Stack extends Azure services to on-premises datacenters.</li>
              <li>Common for regulated industries: healthcare, finance, government.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Deployment Models</tag>
        <tag>Hybrid Cloud</tag>
        <tag>Compliance</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="6" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Regions</title>
      <scenario>Your company needs to deploy resources close to customers in Europe to reduce latency.</scenario>
      <question-text>What is an Azure region?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">A geographical area containing one or more datacenters</choice>
        <choice letter="B">A single datacenter building</choice>
        <choice letter="C">A virtual network boundary</choice>
        <choice letter="D">A subscription billing boundary</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>A region is a set of datacenters in a geographic area connected by low-latency network.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure regions are geographical areas containing multiple datacenters. Choosing a region close to users reduces latency. Some services are region-specific; data residency may require specific regions.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Azure has 60+ regions worldwide, more than any other cloud provider.</li>
              <li>Region pairs provide disaster recovery within the same geography.</li>
              <li>Some regions are restricted (government, sovereign clouds).</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Regions</tag>
        <tag>Geography</tag>
        <tag>Infrastructure</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="7" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Availability Zones</title>
      <scenario>You need to protect an application from a single datacenter failure within a region.</scenario>
      <question-text>What are Azure Availability Zones?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Physically separate datacenters within an Azure region</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Different Azure regions in the same country</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Virtual network segments</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Storage replication options</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Availability zones are separate physical locations within a region with independent power, cooling, and networking.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Availability Zones are unique physical locations within a region. Each zone has independent power, cooling, and networking. Deploying across zones protects against datacenter-level failures.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Not all regions have availability zones; check before designing.</li>
              <li>Zone-redundant services automatically replicate across zones.</li>
              <li>Zonal services let you pin resources to specific zones for control.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Availability Zones</tag>
        <tag>High Availability</tag>
        <tag>Resilience</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="8" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Resource Groups</title>
      <scenario>You're deploying a web application with a database and storage. You want to manage and delete all related resources together.</scenario>
      <question-text>What Azure construct should you use to logically group related resources?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Resource group</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Subscription</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Management group</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure region</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Resource groups are containers for related Azure resources.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>A resource group is a logical container for Azure resources. Resources in a group share a lifecycle and can be managed, monitored, and deleted together. Every Azure resource must belong to exactly one resource group.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Resource groups have a location (for metadata), but resources can be in different regions.</li>
              <li>RBAC and policies can be applied at the resource group level.</li>
              <li>Deleting a resource group deletes all resources inside it.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Resource Groups</tag>
        <tag>Organization</tag>
        <tag>Management</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="9" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Virtual Machines</title>
      <scenario>A company needs to migrate a legacy Windows application that requires specific OS configurations to Azure.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides full control over the operating system and is best for lift-and-shift migrations?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Virtual Machines</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure App Service</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Functions</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Container Instances</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Virtual Machines provide IaaS with full OS control.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Virtual Machines are IaaS offerings that provide full control over the operating system. They're ideal for lift-and-shift migrations where applications need specific OS configurations or cannot be easily modernized.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>You're responsible for OS patching, updates, and security on VMs.</li>
              <li>VMs can run Windows or Linux with various sizes and pricing options.</li>
              <li>Consider Azure Migrate for assessing and migrating on-premises VMs.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Virtual Machines</tag>
        <tag>IaaS</tag>
        <tag>Migration</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="10" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure App Service</title>
      <scenario>A development team wants to deploy a web application without managing servers, with built-in scaling and deployment slots.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service is a fully managed platform for hosting web applications?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure App Service</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Virtual Machines</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Kubernetes Service</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Batch</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>App Service is a PaaS offering for web apps, APIs, and mobile backends.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure App Service is a PaaS platform for hosting web applications, REST APIs, and mobile backends. It handles infrastructure, scaling, and provides features like deployment slots, custom domains, and SSL certificates.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Supports multiple languages: .NET, Java, Node.js, Python, PHP, Ruby.</li>
              <li>Deployment slots enable blue-green deployments with zero downtime.</li>
              <li>App Service plans define compute resources and pricing tiers.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>App Service</tag>
        <tag>PaaS</tag>
        <tag>Web Apps</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="11" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Functions</title>
      <scenario>You need to run code that processes uploaded images only when new files arrive, paying only for execution time.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service allows you to run event-driven code without managing infrastructure?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Functions</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Virtual Machines</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure App Service</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Logic Apps</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Azure Functions is serverless compute that runs code in response to events.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Functions is a serverless compute service that runs code in response to triggers (HTTP requests, timers, queue messages, blob uploads). You pay only for execution time and don't manage servers.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Consumption plan: pay per execution; scales automatically to zero.</li>
              <li>Premium and Dedicated plans offer more control and features.</li>
              <li>Durable Functions extend Functions for stateful orchestrations.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Functions</tag>
        <tag>Serverless</tag>
        <tag>Event-driven</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="12" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Container Instances</title>
      <scenario>You need to quickly run a containerized application without setting up orchestration infrastructure.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service runs containers without requiring you to manage VMs or orchestrators?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Container Instances</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Kubernetes Service</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Virtual Machines</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Batch</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>ACI runs containers on-demand without managing infrastructure.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Container Instances (ACI) provides the fastest way to run containers in Azure without managing VMs or adopting Kubernetes. Ideal for simple applications, task automation, and build jobs.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>ACI supports both Linux and Windows containers.</li>
              <li>Per-second billing based on vCPU and memory.</li>
              <li>For complex orchestration needs, use Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS) instead.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Containers</tag>
        <tag>ACI</tag>
        <tag>Serverless</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="13" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Kubernetes Service</title>
      <scenario>A company needs to deploy and manage a complex microservices application with automatic scaling and self-healing.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides managed Kubernetes for container orchestration?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Container Instances</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure App Service</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Service Fabric</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>AKS is Azure's managed Kubernetes service.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Kubernetes Service (AKS) is a managed container orchestration service. Azure manages the Kubernetes control plane; you manage worker nodes. AKS provides scaling, self-healing, and integration with Azure services.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>AKS control plane is free; you pay only for worker node VMs.</li>
              <li>Integrates with Azure AD, Azure Monitor, and Azure Policy.</li>
              <li>Supports GPU nodes for machine learning workloads.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Kubernetes</tag>
        <tag>AKS</tag>
        <tag>Containers</tag>
        <tag>Orchestration</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="14" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Virtual Network</title>
      <scenario>You need to create an isolated network in Azure where your VMs can communicate securely.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides private network isolation for your resources?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Virtual Network (VNet)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Load Balancer</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure CDN</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure DNS</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Virtual Networks provide isolated network environments in Azure.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Virtual Network (VNet) is the fundamental building block for private networks in Azure. VNets enable Azure resources to securely communicate with each other, the internet, and on-premises networks.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>VNets are scoped to a single region but can connect via peering.</li>
              <li>Subnets segment VNets; NSGs control traffic between subnets.</li>
              <li>VNet peering connects VNets with low-latency, high-bandwidth connections.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Virtual Network</tag>
        <tag>Networking</tag>
        <tag>Security</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="15" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Load Balancer</title>
      <scenario>Your web application runs on multiple VMs and you need to distribute incoming traffic across them.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service distributes network traffic across multiple VMs?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Load Balancer</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Virtual Network</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure VPN Gateway</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Firewall</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Load Balancer distributes traffic to backend resources.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Load Balancer distributes incoming network traffic across multiple VMs or instances. It supports both inbound and outbound scenarios, provides high availability, and operates at Layer 4 (TCP/UDP).</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Basic tier is free; Standard tier offers zone redundancy and more features.</li>
              <li>For Layer 7 (HTTP/HTTPS) load balancing, use Application Gateway.</li>
              <li>Health probes monitor backend health and remove unhealthy instances.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Load Balancer</tag>
        <tag>Networking</tag>
        <tag>High Availability</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="16" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure VPN Gateway</title>
      <scenario>Your company needs to securely connect their on-premises datacenter to Azure over the internet.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service creates encrypted connections between on-premises networks and Azure?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure VPN Gateway</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Load Balancer</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure CDN</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Traffic Manager</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>VPN Gateway provides encrypted site-to-site and point-to-site connections.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure VPN Gateway creates encrypted tunnels between Azure VNets and on-premises networks (site-to-site) or individual clients (point-to-site). Traffic travels over the public internet but is encrypted.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Site-to-site VPN connects entire networks; point-to-site connects individual devices.</li>
              <li>For dedicated private connections without internet, use ExpressRoute.</li>
              <li>VPN Gateway SKUs determine throughput and features.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>VPN Gateway</tag>
        <tag>Hybrid Connectivity</tag>
        <tag>Networking</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="17" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="intermediate">
      <title>Azure ExpressRoute</title>
      <scenario>A financial institution requires a private, dedicated connection to Azure that doesn't traverse the public internet.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides a private connection to Azure through a connectivity provider?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure ExpressRoute</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure VPN Gateway</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Front Door</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Bastion</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>ExpressRoute provides private, dedicated connectivity to Azure.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure ExpressRoute creates private connections between your on-premises infrastructure and Azure datacenters through a connectivity provider. Traffic doesn't traverse the public internet, offering more reliability, faster speeds, and lower latencies.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>ExpressRoute connections are not encrypted by default; consider adding VPN for encryption.</li>
              <li>ExpressRoute Global Reach connects on-premises sites through Microsoft's network.</li>
              <li>Higher cost than VPN but better for consistent, high-bandwidth workloads.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>ExpressRoute</tag>
        <tag>Private Connectivity</tag>
        <tag>Enterprise</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="18" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Blob Storage</title>
      <scenario>You need to store large amounts of unstructured data like images, videos, and backups.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure storage service is optimized for storing massive amounts of unstructured data?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Blob Storage</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Files</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Table Storage</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Queue Storage</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Blob storage is for unstructured data like files, images, and backups.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Blob Storage stores massive amounts of unstructured data (binary large objects). It's ideal for serving images, storing files for distributed access, streaming video, backup and disaster recovery, and data for analysis.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Three blob types: Block blobs (files), Append blobs (logs), Page blobs (VHDs).</li>
              <li>Access tiers: Hot (frequent access), Cool (infrequent), Archive (rare access).</li>
              <li>Lifecycle management policies automate tier transitions.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Blob Storage</tag>
        <tag>Unstructured Data</tag>
        <tag>Storage</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="19" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Files</title>
      <scenario>You need cloud-based file shares accessible via SMB protocol that can replace on-premises file servers.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides fully managed file shares in the cloud?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Files</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Blob Storage</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Disk Storage</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Data Lake Storage</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Azure Files provides SMB and NFS file shares in the cloud.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Files offers fully managed file shares accessible via SMB or NFS protocols. Applications using standard file system APIs can access Azure Files without code changes, making it easy to replace or supplement on-premises file servers.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Azure File Sync caches Azure Files on Windows Servers for local access.</li>
              <li>Supports Azure AD authentication for identity-based access.</li>
              <li>Snapshots provide point-in-time copies for backup.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Azure Files</tag>
        <tag>File Shares</tag>
        <tag>SMB</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="20" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Storage Redundancy Options</title>
      <scenario>You need to store critical data that must survive even if an entire Azure region becomes unavailable.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which storage redundancy option replicates data to a secondary region?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Geo-redundant storage (GRS)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Locally redundant storage (LRS)</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Zone-redundant storage (ZRS)</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Premium storage</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>GRS replicates data to a secondary region hundreds of miles away.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Geo-redundant storage (GRS) replicates data synchronously three times in the primary region, then asynchronously to a secondary region. This protects against regional disasters. RA-GRS adds read access to the secondary.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>LRS: 3 copies in one datacenter (lowest cost).</li>
              <li>ZRS: 3 copies across availability zones in one region.</li>
              <li>GRS: 6 copies total (3 primary + 3 secondary region).</li>
              <li>GZRS combines ZRS in primary region with GRS to secondary.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Storage Redundancy</tag>
        <tag>Disaster Recovery</tag>
        <tag>GRS</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="21" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure SQL Database</title>
      <scenario>You need a relational database for your application without managing SQL Server infrastructure.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides a fully managed relational database based on SQL Server?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure SQL Database</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Cosmos DB</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Table Storage</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Database for MySQL</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Azure SQL Database is a managed SQL Server in the cloud.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure SQL Database is a PaaS relational database service built on SQL Server. Microsoft handles patching, backups, and high availability. It's compatible with most SQL Server features and tools.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Purchasing models: DTU-based (bundled) or vCore-based (flexible).</li>
              <li>Elastic pools share resources among multiple databases cost-effectively.</li>
              <li>For full SQL Server compatibility, consider Azure SQL Managed Instance.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>SQL Database</tag>
        <tag>PaaS</tag>
        <tag>Relational Database</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="22" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Cosmos DB</title>
      <scenario>You need a globally distributed database with single-digit millisecond latency for a mobile gaming application.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure database service provides global distribution with multiple consistency models?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Cosmos DB</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure SQL Database</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Database for PostgreSQL</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Cache for Redis</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Cosmos DB is a globally distributed, multi-model database.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Cosmos DB is a globally distributed NoSQL database with guaranteed single-digit millisecond latency. It supports multiple APIs (SQL, MongoDB, Cassandra, Gremlin, Table) and offers five consistency levels.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Consistency levels range from strong to eventual, balancing latency and consistency.</li>
              <li>Throughput is measured in Request Units (RUs) and can be provisioned or serverless.</li>
              <li>Automatic and instant geo-replication to any Azure region.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Cosmos DB</tag>
        <tag>NoSQL</tag>
        <tag>Global Distribution</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="23" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Microsoft Entra ID (Azure AD)</title>
      <scenario>Your organization needs to manage user identities and control access to Azure resources and Microsoft 365.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which service provides cloud-based identity and access management?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Microsoft Entra ID (Azure Active Directory)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Key Vault</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Microsoft Defender for Cloud</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Policy</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Microsoft Entra ID is Azure's identity and access management service.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Microsoft Entra ID (formerly Azure Active Directory) is a cloud-based identity service. It provides authentication, single sign-on (SSO), multi-factor authentication (MFA), and conditional access for users accessing Azure, Microsoft 365, and thousands of SaaS apps.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Not the same as on-premises Active Directory; different protocols and purpose.</li>
              <li>Azure AD Connect syncs on-premises AD with Entra ID for hybrid identity.</li>
              <li>Editions: Free, P1, P2 with increasing features (P2 includes Identity Protection).</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Entra ID</tag>
        <tag>Identity</tag>
        <tag>Authentication</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="24" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Multi-Factor Authentication</title>
      <scenario>Your security team requires users to verify their identity using more than just a password.</scenario>
      <question-text>What security feature requires multiple forms of verification before granting access?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Multi-factor authentication (MFA)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Single sign-on (SSO)</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Role-based access control (RBAC)</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Conditional Access</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>MFA requires something you know, have, or are.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Multi-factor authentication (MFA) requires two or more verification methods: something you know (password), something you have (phone, security key), or something you are (biometrics). MFA dramatically reduces the risk of compromised accounts.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Microsoft Authenticator app, SMS, phone call, or hardware tokens are common second factors.</li>
              <li>Security defaults in Entra ID enable MFA for all users at no extra cost.</li>
              <li>Passwordless authentication (FIDO2, Windows Hello) is even more secure than traditional MFA.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>MFA</tag>
        <tag>Authentication</tag>
        <tag>Security</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="25" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="intermediate">
      <title>Conditional Access</title>
      <scenario>You want to require MFA only when users access sensitive applications from outside the corporate network.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Entra ID feature allows you to enforce access policies based on conditions like location or device state?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Conditional Access</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Multi-factor authentication</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure RBAC</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Policy</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Conditional Access creates if-then policies for access control.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Conditional Access policies in Entra ID enable adaptive access control. Policies evaluate signals (user, location, device, app, risk) and enforce decisions (allow, block, require MFA). This enables zero-trust security.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Requires Entra ID P1 or P2 license.</li>
              <li>Common conditions: user/group, application, device platform, location, sign-in risk.</li>
              <li>Always create break-glass accounts excluded from restrictive policies.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Conditional Access</tag>
        <tag>Zero Trust</tag>
        <tag>Identity</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="26" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Key Vault</title>
      <scenario>Your application needs to securely store API keys, connection strings, and certificates.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides secure storage for secrets, keys, and certificates?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Key Vault</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Storage</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Microsoft Entra ID</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Security Center</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Key Vault securely stores and manages secrets, keys, and certificates.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Key Vault is a cloud service for securely storing and accessing secrets (API keys, passwords, connection strings), cryptographic keys, and certificates. Access is controlled through RBAC and access policies.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Secrets are encrypted at rest; keys can be hardware-protected (HSM-backed).</li>
              <li>Applications authenticate to Key Vault using managed identities (no credentials in code).</li>
              <li>Soft-delete and purge protection prevent accidental or malicious deletion.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Key Vault</tag>
        <tag>Secrets Management</tag>
        <tag>Security</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="27" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Network Security Groups</title>
      <scenario>You need to control which traffic can reach your VMs by filtering based on source IP and port.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure resource filters network traffic to and from Azure resources in a virtual network?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Network Security Group (NSG)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Firewall</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Load Balancer</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Application Gateway</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>NSGs filter traffic with allow/deny rules based on source, destination, and port.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Network Security Groups (NSGs) contain security rules that filter inbound and outbound traffic. Rules specify source/destination IP, port, and protocol. NSGs can be associated with subnets or individual network interfaces.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Rules are processed by priority (lower number = higher priority).</li>
              <li>Default rules allow VNet traffic and outbound internet; deny inbound internet.</li>
              <li>Application Security Groups (ASGs) simplify rules by grouping VMs logically.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>NSG</tag>
        <tag>Network Security</tag>
        <tag>Firewall Rules</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="28" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="intermediate">
      <title>Azure Firewall</title>
      <scenario>You need a centralized, fully managed firewall with threat intelligence and application-level filtering for your entire Azure network.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides stateful firewall capabilities with built-in high availability?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Firewall</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Network Security Groups</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure DDoS Protection</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure VPN Gateway</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Azure Firewall is a managed, cloud-based network security service.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Firewall is a managed, stateful firewall service with built-in high availability and unrestricted cloud scalability. It provides application FQDN filtering, network traffic filtering, and threat intelligence-based filtering.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Standard tier for Layer 3-7 filtering; Premium adds TLS inspection and IDPS.</li>
              <li>Azure Firewall Manager provides central policy management across subscriptions.</li>
              <li>NSGs are per-subnet/NIC; Azure Firewall is a centralized network appliance.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Azure Firewall</tag>
        <tag>Network Security</tag>
        <tag>Threat Protection</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="29" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Microsoft Defender for Cloud</title>
      <scenario>You need to assess your Azure security posture and get recommendations for improving security.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides security posture management and threat protection across your cloud workloads?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Microsoft Defender for Cloud</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Key Vault</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Policy</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Monitor</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Defender for Cloud provides security recommendations and threat protection.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Microsoft Defender for Cloud (formerly Azure Security Center) provides unified security management across Azure, hybrid, and multi-cloud environments. It includes security posture management (free) and advanced threat protection (paid plans).</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Secure Score measures security posture; higher is better.</li>
              <li>Defender plans protect specific workloads: VMs, SQL, Storage, Containers, etc.</li>
              <li>Integrates with Microsoft Sentinel for SIEM/SOAR capabilities.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Defender for Cloud</tag>
        <tag>Security Posture</tag>
        <tag>Threat Protection</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="30" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure DDoS Protection</title>
      <scenario>Your public-facing web application needs protection against distributed denial-of-service attacks.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides protection against volumetric DDoS attacks?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure DDoS Protection</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Firewall</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Network Security Groups</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Front Door</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>DDoS Protection defends against distributed denial-of-service attacks.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure DDoS Protection provides defense against DDoS attacks for Azure resources. Basic protection is automatic and free. Standard tier adds adaptive tuning, attack analytics, and cost protection guarantee.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Basic: Automatic protection for all Azure services at no additional cost.</li>
              <li>Standard: Enhanced protection with real-time metrics and DDoS Rapid Response team.</li>
              <li>Standard includes cost protection: credits for scale-out costs during attacks.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>DDoS Protection</tag>
        <tag>Network Security</tag>
        <tag>Attack Mitigation</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="31" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Defense in Depth</title>
      <scenario>Your security architect recommends implementing multiple layers of security controls.</scenario>
      <question-text>What security strategy uses multiple layers of protection to slow down attackers?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Defense in depth</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Single sign-on</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Least privilege</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Zero trust</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Defense in depth uses multiple security layers so one breach doesn't compromise everything.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Defense in depth is a security strategy using multiple layers: physical security, identity/access, perimeter, network, compute, application, and data. If one layer is breached, others continue to provide protection.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Layers: Physical, Identity, Perimeter, Network, Compute, Application, Data.</li>
              <li>Each layer uses different security mechanisms and controls.</li>
              <li>Complements zero trust (never trust, always verify) principles.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Defense in Depth</tag>
        <tag>Security Strategy</tag>
        <tag>Layered Security</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="32" category-ref="cat-governance" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Policy</title>
      <scenario>Your organization needs to ensure all VMs are deployed only in approved regions and with required tags.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service enforces organizational standards and assesses compliance at scale?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Policy</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure RBAC</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Blueprints</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Microsoft Entra ID</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Azure Policy enforces rules and effects for your resources.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Policy creates, assigns, and manages policies that enforce rules on resources. Policies can prevent non-compliant resources (deny), audit existing resources, or automatically remediate non-compliance. Initiatives group related policies.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Effects include: Deny, Audit, Append, Modify, DeployIfNotExists.</li>
              <li>Assign policies at management group, subscription, or resource group scope.</li>
              <li>Built-in policies cover common scenarios; custom policies use JSON definitions.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Azure Policy</tag>
        <tag>Governance</tag>
        <tag>Compliance</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="33" category-ref="cat-governance" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure RBAC</title>
      <scenario>You need to grant a developer read-only access to a specific resource group without giving them access to other resources.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure feature provides fine-grained access management for Azure resources?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Role-based access control (RBAC)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Policy</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Network Security Groups</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Key Vault</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>RBAC assigns permissions to users, groups, and service principals.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure RBAC manages who has access to Azure resources, what they can do, and at what scope. Role assignments combine a security principal (who), role definition (what permissions), and scope (where it applies).</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Built-in roles: Owner, Contributor, Reader, plus hundreds of service-specific roles.</li>
              <li>Scope hierarchy: Management group > Subscription > Resource group > Resource.</li>
              <li>Permissions inherit down the scope hierarchy; use least privilege principle.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>RBAC</tag>
        <tag>Access Control</tag>
        <tag>Security</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="34" category-ref="cat-governance" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Resource Locks</title>
      <scenario>You need to prevent accidental deletion of a production database, even by administrators.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure feature prevents resources from being accidentally deleted or modified?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Resource locks</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Policy</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure RBAC</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Network Security Groups</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Resource locks prevent deletion or modification regardless of RBAC permissions.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Resource locks protect resources from accidental deletion or modification. Two lock types exist: CanNotDelete (allows read and modify, blocks delete) and ReadOnly (allows read only). Locks apply regardless of RBAC permissions.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Locks can be applied at subscription, resource group, or resource level.</li>
              <li>Locks are inherited by child resources.</li>
              <li>Only Owner and User Access Administrator can create or delete locks.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Resource Locks</tag>
        <tag>Protection</tag>
        <tag>Governance</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="35" category-ref="cat-governance" difficulty="intermediate">
      <title>Azure Blueprints</title>
      <scenario>Your organization needs to repeatedly deploy compliant environments with predefined resources, policies, and RBAC assignments.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service packages ARM templates, policies, and RBAC into reusable environment definitions?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Blueprints</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Policy</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Resource Manager</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Automation</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Blueprints package policies, RBAC, and ARM templates for repeatable deployments.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Blueprints orchestrate deployment of resource templates, policy assignments, role assignments, and resource groups as a single versioned package. Blueprints maintain the relationship between definition and deployment for tracking and auditing.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Blueprints differ from ARM templates: they track what was deployed and maintain the relationship.</li>
              <li>Blueprint artifacts include: ARM templates, policy assignments, role assignments, resource groups.</li>
              <li>Useful for landing zones and standardized environment provisioning.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Blueprints</tag>
        <tag>Governance</tag>
        <tag>Automation</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="36" category-ref="cat-governance" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Tags</title>
      <scenario>Your finance team needs to track cloud costs by department and project across hundreds of resources.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure feature allows you to organize resources with name-value pairs for cost management and organization?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Tags</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Resource groups</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Subscriptions</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Management groups</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Tags are metadata name-value pairs applied to resources.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Tags are name-value pairs that let you categorize and organize Azure resources. Common uses include cost allocation, environment identification (dev/prod), owner tracking, and automation triggers. Tags can be enforced via Azure Policy.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Resources can have up to 50 tags; some resources don't support tags.</li>
              <li>Tags don't inherit from resource groups; use Policy to enforce inheritance.</li>
              <li>Cost Management can filter and group costs by tags for chargeback.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Tags</tag>
        <tag>Organization</tag>
        <tag>Cost Management</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="37" category-ref="cat-governance" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Management Groups</title>
      <scenario>Your enterprise has 50 subscriptions across multiple business units and needs to apply consistent governance policies.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure construct organizes subscriptions into a hierarchy for unified policy and access management?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Management groups</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Resource groups</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure regions</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Availability zones</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Management groups organize subscriptions and apply policies across them.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Management groups provide a governance scope above subscriptions. You can organize subscriptions into containers (management groups) and apply policies and RBAC that automatically inherit to all subscriptions beneath.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Up to 6 levels of depth (excluding root and subscription level).</li>
              <li>Each directory has a single root management group.</li>
              <li>10,000 management groups per directory; each can have only one parent.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Management Groups</tag>
        <tag>Governance</tag>
        <tag>Hierarchy</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="38" category-ref="cat-pricing" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Subscriptions</title>
      <scenario>Your company needs to separate billing for development and production environments.</scenario>
      <question-text>What is an Azure subscription?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">A billing and access boundary for Azure resources</choice>
        <choice letter="B">A container for resource groups only</choice>
        <choice letter="C">A type of Azure support plan</choice>
        <choice letter="D">A geographic deployment region</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Subscriptions are billing units and access boundaries in Azure.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>An Azure subscription is a logical unit that links Azure services to an Azure account. It serves as a billing boundary (separate invoices) and an access control boundary (RBAC scope). Organizations often use multiple subscriptions for isolation.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Subscription types: Pay-As-You-Go, Enterprise Agreement, CSP, Free trial.</li>
              <li>Each subscription has limits/quotas that can be increased via support requests.</li>
              <li>Use management groups to organize multiple subscriptions.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Subscriptions</tag>
        <tag>Billing</tag>
        <tag>Organization</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="39" category-ref="cat-pricing" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Factors Affecting Cost</title>
      <scenario>You're estimating the cost of running a VM in Azure and need to understand what factors influence pricing.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which factor does NOT typically affect the cost of an Azure virtual machine?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">The name of the resource group</choice>
        <choice letter="B">The VM size and series</choice>
        <choice letter="C">The Azure region</choice>
        <choice letter="D">The operating system</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Resource group names are just labels; they don't affect pricing.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure VM costs depend on: VM size (vCPUs, memory), region (prices vary by location), OS (Windows costs more than Linux due to licensing), and runtime hours. Resource group names are organizational and don't impact cost.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Additional costs: storage, networking (egress), public IPs, backup.</li>
              <li>Reserved Instances and Spot VMs offer significant discounts.</li>
              <li>Azure Hybrid Benefit reduces cost for existing Windows Server/SQL licenses.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Pricing</tag>
        <tag>Cost Factors</tag>
        <tag>Virtual Machines</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="40" category-ref="cat-pricing" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Pricing Calculator</title>
      <scenario>Before deploying to Azure, you need to estimate the monthly cost of your planned resources.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which tool helps you estimate the cost of Azure services before deployment?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Pricing Calculator</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Cost Management</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Advisor</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Monitor</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>The Pricing Calculator estimates costs before you deploy anything.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>The Azure Pricing Calculator is a web tool for estimating costs before deployment. You configure products, regions, and options to get monthly cost estimates. It helps with budgeting and comparing configurations.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>TCO Calculator compares on-premises vs. Azure costs for migration decisions.</li>
              <li>Cost Management + Billing analyzes actual spending after deployment.</li>
              <li>Save and share estimates; export to Excel for detailed analysis.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Pricing Calculator</tag>
        <tag>Cost Estimation</tag>
        <tag>Planning</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="41" category-ref="cat-pricing" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Cost Management</title>
      <scenario>You need to analyze your actual Azure spending and identify cost optimization opportunities.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service helps you monitor, allocate, and optimize cloud costs?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Cost Management + Billing</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Pricing Calculator</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Advisor</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Policy</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Cost Management analyzes actual spending and helps optimize costs.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Cost Management + Billing provides tools to monitor, allocate, and optimize Azure costs. Features include cost analysis, budgets with alerts, recommendations, and exports. It works with Azure, AWS, and GCP (multi-cloud).</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Cost analysis views: by resource, resource group, service, tag, location.</li>
              <li>Budgets trigger alerts or automation when thresholds are reached.</li>
              <li>Exports automate data delivery to storage accounts for external analysis.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Cost Management</tag>
        <tag>Billing</tag>
        <tag>Optimization</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="42" category-ref="cat-pricing" difficulty="intermediate">
      <title>Azure Reservations</title>
      <scenario>Your organization runs stable, predictable workloads and wants to reduce VM costs significantly.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which purchasing option offers the largest discount for committing to one or three years of usage?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Reservations</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Spot Virtual Machines</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Pay-As-You-Go pricing</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Free Account</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Reservations provide up to 72% discount for 1 or 3-year commitments.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Reservations offer significant discounts (up to 72%) compared to pay-as-you-go prices in exchange for committing to 1 or 3-year terms. Available for VMs, SQL Database, Cosmos DB, storage, and other services.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Reservations are scope-flexible: can apply to subscription, resource group, or be shared.</li>
              <li>Can exchange or refund reservations with some limitations.</li>
              <li>Combine with Azure Hybrid Benefit for maximum savings.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Reservations</tag>
        <tag>Cost Savings</tag>
        <tag>Commitment</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="43" category-ref="cat-pricing" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Advisor</title>
      <scenario>You want personalized recommendations to improve the reliability, security, and cost-effectiveness of your Azure deployments.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides personalized best practice recommendations?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Advisor</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Monitor</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Policy</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Microsoft Defender for Cloud</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Azure Advisor analyzes your configurations and provides recommendations.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Advisor analyzes your deployed resources and usage patterns to provide personalized recommendations across five categories: Reliability, Security, Performance, Cost, and Operational Excellence.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Advisor is free and automatically analyzes your resources.</li>
              <li>Recommendations include estimated savings for cost optimizations.</li>
              <li>Can postpone or dismiss recommendations; configure alert rules.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Azure Advisor</tag>
        <tag>Recommendations</tag>
        <tag>Best Practices</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="44" category-ref="cat-pricing" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Service Level Agreements</title>
      <scenario>Your business needs to understand the uptime guarantees Microsoft provides for Azure services.</scenario>
      <question-text>What document defines the uptime commitments and compensation terms for Azure services?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Service Level Agreement (SLA)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Policy</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Advisor report</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Pricing Calculator estimate</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>SLAs define uptime guarantees and service credits for downtime.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Service Level Agreements (SLAs) are formal documents defining Microsoft's commitment to uptime and connectivity. SLAs specify uptime percentages (e.g., 99.99%) and service credits if commitments aren't met.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>SLAs vary by service and configuration (e.g., VMs in availability zones vs. single VM).</li>
              <li>Preview services have no SLA; check before using in production.</li>
              <li>Composite SLA: multiply individual SLAs to calculate overall application SLA.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>SLA</tag>
        <tag>Uptime</tag>
        <tag>Reliability</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="45" category-ref="cat-pricing" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Support Plans</title>
      <scenario>Your production workload requires 24/7 technical support with rapid response times.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure support plan provides 24/7 access to technical support for severity A issues?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Standard, Professional Direct, or Premier</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Basic only</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Developer only</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Free tier only</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>24/7 support requires Standard or higher support plans.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure support plans range from Basic (free, no technical support) to Premier. Standard, Professional Direct, and Premier plans include 24/7 technical support. Response times improve with higher tiers.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Basic: Free, self-help, billing support only.</li>
              <li>Developer: Business hours support, not for production.</li>
              <li>Standard: 24/7 for critical issues; Professional Direct adds faster response.</li>
              <li>Premier: Designated Technical Account Manager, on-site support.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Support Plans</tag>
        <tag>Technical Support</tag>
        <tag>Enterprise</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="46" category-ref="cat-governance" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Monitor</title>
      <scenario>You need to collect and analyze telemetry data from your Azure resources to identify performance issues.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service collects and analyzes metrics and logs from Azure resources?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Monitor</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Advisor</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Policy</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Microsoft Defender for Cloud</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Azure Monitor is the central service for metrics, logs, and alerts.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Monitor collects, analyzes, and acts on telemetry from Azure and on-premises environments. It includes metrics (numeric data), logs (structured records), and enables alerts, dashboards, and automated responses.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Log Analytics workspaces store and query logs using KQL (Kusto Query Language).</li>
              <li>Application Insights monitors application performance (APM).</li>
              <li>Alerts can trigger actions: emails, SMS, webhooks, Azure Functions, Logic Apps.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Azure Monitor</tag>
        <tag>Monitoring</tag>
        <tag>Observability</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="47" category-ref="cat-governance" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Service Health</title>
      <scenario>You need to be notified when Azure service issues might affect your resources.</scenario>
      <question-text>Which Azure service provides personalized alerts about Azure service incidents and planned maintenance?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Service Health</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Monitor</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Advisor</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Status page</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Service Health provides personalized Azure status for your resources.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Service Health provides personalized information about Azure service issues, planned maintenance, and health advisories that affect your specific resources. Unlike the public Azure Status page, it's tailored to your subscriptions and regions.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Three components: Azure Status (global), Service Health (your services), Resource Health (specific resources).</li>
              <li>Create health alerts to get notifications via email, SMS, or webhooks.</li>
              <li>Root cause analyses are published after major incidents.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Service Health</tag>
        <tag>Monitoring</tag>
        <tag>Alerts</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="48" category-ref="cat-core-services" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Azure Resource Manager</title>
      <scenario>You want to deploy infrastructure consistently using templates and manage resources as a group.</scenario>
      <question-text>What is the deployment and management service for Azure that enables infrastructure as code?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Azure Resource Manager (ARM)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Portal</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure CLI</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure PowerShell</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>ARM is the management layer that handles all resource operations.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>Azure Resource Manager (ARM) is the deployment and management service for Azure. All requests (Portal, CLI, PowerShell, APIs) go through ARM. ARM templates and Bicep enable declarative infrastructure as code deployments.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>ARM provides consistent management layer, access control, tags, and locks.</li>
              <li>ARM templates are JSON; Bicep is a simpler DSL that compiles to ARM.</li>
              <li>Templates enable idempotent deployments: same template = same result.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>ARM</tag>
        <tag>Infrastructure as Code</tag>
        <tag>Templates</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="49" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Shared Responsibility Model</title>
      <scenario>Your security team needs to understand who is responsible for what in cloud security.</scenario>
      <question-text>In the shared responsibility model for PaaS, who is responsible for patching the operating system?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Microsoft (the cloud provider)</choice>
        <choice letter="B">The customer</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Both equally</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Neither - it's automated</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>In PaaS, Microsoft manages the platform including OS patching.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>The shared responsibility model divides security responsibilities between cloud provider and customer. In PaaS, Microsoft handles physical security, host infrastructure, and OS patching. Customers are responsible for their data, identities, and applications.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>IaaS: Customer manages OS and above; more responsibility than PaaS.</li>
              <li>SaaS: Most responsibility with provider; customer manages data and access.</li>
              <li>Customer always responsible for: data, endpoints, accounts, access management.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Shared Responsibility</tag>
        <tag>Security</tag>
        <tag>Cloud Model</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>

    <question id="50" category-ref="cat-security" difficulty="basic">
      <title>Compliance and Trust</title>
      <scenario>Your company operates in healthcare and needs to verify Azure meets HIPAA requirements.</scenario>
      <question-text>Where can you find details about Azure's compliance certifications and regulatory standards?</question-text>
      <choices>
        <choice letter="A">Microsoft Trust Center and Azure compliance documentation</choice>
        <choice letter="B">Azure Pricing Calculator</choice>
        <choice letter="C">Azure Advisor</choice>
        <choice letter="D">Azure Service Health</choice>
      </choices>
      <correct-answer>A</correct-answer>
      <hints>
        <hint level="1" label="Brief Hint">
          <content>Trust Center provides compliance documentation and certifications.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="2" label="Complete Explanation">
          <content>The Microsoft Trust Center provides information about Microsoft's approach to security, privacy, and compliance. Azure compliance documentation details specific certifications (HIPAA, SOC, ISO, GDPR, etc.) and provides audit reports.</content>
        </hint>
        <hint level="3" label="Deep Knowledge">
          <content>
            <ul>
              <li>Service Trust Portal provides audit reports and compliance guides.</li>
              <li>Azure has 100+ compliance offerings across industries and regions.</li>
              <li>Compliance is shared: Azure provides compliant infrastructure; you must use it properly.</li>
            </ul>
          </content>
        </hint>
      </hints>
      <tags>
        <tag>Compliance</tag>
        <tag>Trust Center</tag>
        <tag>Regulatory</tag>
      </tags>
    </question>
  </questions>

  <glossary>
    <term id="gl-iaas" category="Service Models">
      <name>Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS)</name>
      <definition>Cloud computing model where the provider manages physical hardware and virtualization; customer manages OS and above.</definition>
      <exam-note>You're responsible for OS patching and security in IaaS.</exam-note>
      <related-terms>
        <term-ref>PaaS</term-ref>
        <term-ref>SaaS</term-ref>
      </related-terms>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-paas" category="Service Models">
      <name>Platform as a Service (PaaS)</name>
      <definition>Cloud computing model where the provider manages hardware through runtime; customer manages applications and data.</definition>
      <exam-note>Azure App Service and Azure SQL Database are PaaS examples.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-saas" category="Service Models">
      <name>Software as a Service (SaaS)</name>
      <definition>Cloud computing model where the provider manages everything; customer uses the software.</definition>
      <exam-note>Microsoft 365 is a SaaS example.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-region" category="Infrastructure">
      <name>Azure Region</name>
      <definition>A geographical area containing one or more datacenters networked together with low-latency connections.</definition>
      <exam-note>Choose regions based on latency, compliance, and service availability.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-az" category="Infrastructure">
      <name>Availability Zone</name>
      <definition>Unique physical locations within an Azure region with independent power, cooling, and networking.</definition>
      <exam-note>Deploying across zones provides 99.99% SLA for VMs.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-rg" category="Management">
      <name>Resource Group</name>
      <definition>A logical container for Azure resources that share the same lifecycle.</definition>
      <exam-note>Resources can only belong to one resource group; deleting RG deletes all contents.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-subscription" category="Management">
      <name>Subscription</name>
      <definition>A billing and access control boundary in Azure that links services to an account.</definition>
      <exam-note>Use multiple subscriptions for billing separation and access isolation.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-mgmt-group" category="Management">
      <name>Management Group</name>
      <definition>A container for organizing subscriptions and applying governance across them.</definition>
      <exam-note>Policies and RBAC assigned to management groups inherit to child subscriptions.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-entra-id" category="Identity">
      <name>Microsoft Entra ID</name>
      <definition>Microsoft's cloud-based identity and access management service (formerly Azure Active Directory).</definition>
      <exam-note>Provides authentication, SSO, MFA, and Conditional Access.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-rbac" category="Security">
      <name>Role-Based Access Control (RBAC)</name>
      <definition>Authorization system for managing access to Azure resources based on roles assigned to users, groups, or service principals.</definition>
      <exam-note>Follows least privilege principle; roles inherit down the scope hierarchy.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-policy" category="Governance">
      <name>Azure Policy</name>
      <definition>Service for creating, assigning, and managing policies that enforce rules on Azure resources.</definition>
      <exam-note>Use Policy for compliance; use RBAC for access control.</exam-note>
    </term>
    <term id="gl-sla" category="Pricing">
      <name>Service Level Agreement (SLA)</name>
      <definition>A formal agreement defining uptime commitments and compensation for Azure services.</definition>
      <exam-note>SLAs vary by service and configuration; preview services have no SLA.</exam-note>
    </term>
  </glossary>
</certification-exam>
